# Rakibul Islam

**Email**: raakibul.uap@gmail.com **Website**: https://raaakibul.github.io/

**Phone**: +880-1315396692 https://github.com/raaakibul 271/24, Niribili House, Sankar, Mohammadpur 1207, Dhaka, Bangladesh

#### **Research Interests**

As a dedicated learner, I investigate the possible benefits of Artificial Intelligence technology to enhance human life. My research interest areas are including machine learning, deep learning and artificial intelligence in the design and implementation of research tools. My primary purpose is to develop widely implementable machine and deep learning-based solutions for real scenarios in artificial technology.

Research Areas: Artificial Intelligence, Image Processing and Computer Vision, Machine Learning, Deep Learning.

#### **Education**

 $September\ 2018-June\ 2023$ 

Dhaka, Bangladesh

# **Bachelor of Computer Science and Engineering**

University of Asia Pacific

Thesis Topic: Deep Learning-Based Background Noise Classification

and Reduction for Audio Enhancement.

Thesis Supervisor: Rashik Rahman, Lecturer; University of Asia Pacific

*Major Courses:* Structured Programming, Data Structure and Algorithms, Object Oriented Programming, Database, Software Engineering, Computer Networks, Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Probability & Statistics, Data Communications, etc.

## **Research Experience**

Sept. 2022 – Dec. 2022	
------------------------	--

# Dhaka, Bangladesh

# **Bdian Research Trainee**

Instructor: Md. Fazle Rabbi Afsar, Researcher at Youth society For Research and Action.

- Understanding the research methodology in real problem scenario.
- Propose the research topic, design and methodology.

### **Industrial Experience**

Jan 2022 – May 2023 Dhaka, Bangladesh

#### Industrial Trainee, BrogrammersLab

Software Engr Intern

Supervisor: Rafi Rahman

- I've learned that all team members should maintain a clear line of communication and collaborate effectively.
- During this internship, I've learned how to solve problems calmly; no matter what happens, we should intend to solve any arising problem.
- The Most important thing that I've learned throughout this internship is to maintain time.

#### **Professional Activities**

Oct. 2023 - Present

Dhaka, Bangladesh

#### CareTutors

Largest online and offline based tutoring platform.

• I gave in-person lessons on physics, chemistry, mathematics and programming Languages (Python, C, C++ and JavaScript) to high school and college level students. I have experiences on conducting classes for small group of students, grading their tests, posting their grade, providing them feedback, and also preparing them for lab experiments, and monitoring their progress.

#### **Skills**

Programming Languages: Python, JavaScript, SQL, C/C++, Java

**Python Packages:** Pytorch, OpenCV, Pandas, Matplotlib, Keras, Sci-kit learn, TensorFlow **Web Technologies:** HTML, CSS, SASC, Bootstrap, JavaScript, TypeScript, React, Json **Tools:** Microsoft Word, Latex, Visual Studio, Microsoft SQL Server, MySQL, Power BI, Git

Project Management: Communication Skills (Written & Verbal), Quantitative Skills, Initiative, Interpersonal

Skills, Teamwork, Time Management, etc.

Languages: English (Native), Bengali (Fluent)

## **Professional Training and Certificates**

2024 - Mathematics for Machine Learning and Data Science (3 Courses) by Luis Serrano | DeepLearning.AI

- Linear Algebra for Machine Learning and Data Science
- Calculus for Machine Learning and Data Science
- Probability & Statistics for Machine Learning & Data Science

2024 - Machine Learning Specialization (3 Courses) by Andrew NG | DeepLearning.AI & Stanford University

- Supervised Machine Learning: Regression and Classification
- Advanced Learning Algorithms
- Unsupervised Learning, Recommenders, Reinforcement Learning

2024 - Learn SQL Basics for Data Science Specialization (1 Course) | University of California, Davis

• SQL for Data Science by Sadie St. Lawrence

2024 - IBM Data Analyst Professional Certificate (1 Course) | IBM

• Data Visualization with Python by Saishruthi Swaminathan and Dr. Pooja

2024 - Data Science Foundations Specialization (1 Course) | IBM

What is Data Science by Alex Aklson

2024 - Google Data Analytics Professional Certificate (1 Course) | Google

• Foundations: Data, Data, Everywhere

2022 - Bdian Research Trainee certificate

#### **Thesis Publications**

Deep Learning-Based Background Noise Classification and Reduction for Audio Enhancement. – under review

## References

Tanjina Helaly (Advisor) Assistant Professor, University of Asia Pacific Department of Computer Science and Engineering

Dr. Aloke Kumar Saha Professor, University of Asia Pacific Department of Computer Science and Engineering Rashik Rahman (Thesis Supervisor) Lecturer, University of Asia Pacific Department of Computer Science and Engineering